Finding Aid for the Byron McAfee Papers LSC.0339
UCLA Library Special Collections
- III. Manuscripts, 1553-1864.; 1 box.
  - [Petition by the people of Coatlan de Puertos Abaxo], Coatlan, 1637 July 1.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 42)
    4 leaves: paper; 310 x 217 mm. Petition charging mistreatment by the hands of the curate, Antonio Bautista. Received by the Bishop of Guadalajara, don Leonel de Cervantes y Carvajal. Two petitions in Nahuatl, and authorized translations in Spanish.
  - [Contract for sale of land], Azcapotzalco, 1737 August 1.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 43)
    1 bifolium: paper; 310 x 211 mm. Purchase of land by Don Antonio Gonzalez Tercero, presumably from the municipal council. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Inventory of the estate of Francisco Felipe, with funeral expenses and auction of effects], Analcotitlan, 1652 March 17.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 44)
    1 bifolium: paper; 314 x 215 mm. Inventory of the property, and summary of expenses and auction. Signed by witnesses and notary. Text in Nahuatl. (Anderson, 78)
  - [Contract for sale of land], Azcapotzalco, 1735 June 20.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 45)
    1 bifolium: paper; 307 x 211 mm. Land purchase by Antonio Gonzalez from Jacinto Ventura. Ventura received the land as an inheritance from his sister, Anxelina Maria. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Contract for sale of land], Atzcapotzalco, 1738 November 4.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 46)
    1 leaf: paper; 310 x 212 mm. Land purchase by Don Juan Soriano and his wife, Doña Manuela Antonia y Garcia, from Phelipe de Santiago, a widower of Josepha de la Encarnacíon, of San Simon Pochtlan. Mentions testament of Don Pascual de los Reyes. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Testament of Pedro Cayetano], San Juan Bautista, Metepec, 1792 February 14.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 47)
    1 leaf: paper; 309 x 210 mm. Final will and testament, with mention of his wife, Maura Maria. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Contract for sale of land], Atzcapotzalco, 1738 October 15.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 48)
    1 leaf: paper; 308 x 215 mm. Purchase of land by Don Juan Soriano and his wife, Doña Manuela Antonia y Garcia, from Marco Antonio and his wife, Maria Teresa of San Simon Pochtlan. Mentions testament of Don Pascual de los Reyes. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Contracts for sale of land], Atzcapotzalco, 1705 May 5-1722 May 6.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 49)
    8 leaves: paper; 307 x 212 mm. Documentation regarding the lands of Angelina Maria in San Simon Pochutla (See MS 4.) Includes reference to Phelipe de Santiago and other names, and lands in San Domingo. Stamp of King Philip V on all leaves. Text in Nahuatl, with some Spanish vocabulary throughout.
  - [Petition for removal of the priest of Jalostotitlan], Guadalajara, 1611 December 16-1612 January 10.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 5)
    14 leaves: paper; 315 x 216 mm. Criminal complaint brought by Juan Vicente, alcalde, and Miguel López against Francisco Muñoz Bohorques, cura of Xalostotitlan. Questionnaire, in Nahuatl, ff. 1-3; Spanish translation, ff. 4-7; testimony, in Spanish, ff. 8-13v. Complaint includes charges of the cura's illicit relationship with a woman, violence against and beatings of native peoples, and coercive acts with Spanish officials. (Anderson, 166)
  - [Notation on the completion of a testamentary mandate to say mass], Mexico, 1553 March 10.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 50)
    1 leaf: paper; 153 x 210 mm. Fragment. Appears to be a notation or receipt for the saying of mass, signed by Fray Diego de Orivez.
  - [Contract for sale of land], Atzcapotzalco, 1738 November 20.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 51)
    1 leaf: paper; 309 x 215 mm. Purchase of land by Don Juan Soriano and his wife, Doña Manuela Antonio y Garcia from Andres de los Reyes and his wife, Luisa Francisco, of San Simon Pochtlan. Sale appears to be the result of the testament of Don Pascual de los Reyes, taken in 1732 September 4. Text in Nahuatl. Stamp of King Philip V on recto. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Receipt for debt], San Juan Bautista, Metepec, 1781 January 13.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 52)
    1 leaf: paper; 310 x 215 mm. Deals with a debt, possibly in the context of a testament. Stamp of King Philip V on recto. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Contract for sale of land], Atzcapotzalco, 1745 November 15.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 53)
    1 leaf: paper; 311 x 216 mm. Purchase of land by Don Juan Soriano and his wife, Doña Manuela Antonio y Garcia, from Don Juan Ignacion Marquez, his wife, Manuela Josepha, and children, Isabel Maria, Francisco Paula, and Julain Valentin, of San Martin Xochahuac. Stamp of King Philip V on recto. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Contract for sale of land], Atzcapotzalco, 1745 April 14.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 54)
    2 leaves: paper; 310 x 218 mm. Purchase of land by Don Juan Soriano and his wife, Doña Manuela Antonia y Garcia, from Don Bartolome de Vargas, his wife Doña Maria, and their children, Margarita Simona and Maria del Carmen, of San Mateo. Both leaves bear the stamp of King Philip V on the recto. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Contract for sale of land], San Juan Bautista, Metepec, 1738 October 5.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 55)
    1 leaf: paper; 312 x 216 mm. Purchase of land by Don Juan Soriano and his wife, Doña Manuela Antonia y Garcia, from Francisca Maria, a widow, of San Simon Pochtla, and her son Santiago Cristobal. Mentions the will of Don Pascual de los Reyes, "notlazotatzin." Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Contract for sale of land], San Juan Bautista, Metepec, 1726 November 17, 1810 September 10.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 56)
    3 leaves: paper; 310 x 212 mm. Includes an original 1726 contract, in Nahuatl, and an 1810 certification of the sale, in Spanish. Purchase of land by Don Juan de los Santos from Son Cruz de los Santos Castañeda and his wife, Doña Barbara Severina. Stamped. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Testimony regarding certification of land], San Lucas, Tlacochcalco, 1785 October 14.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 57)
    1 bifolium: paper; 306 x 215 mm. Testimony taken by Juan Hilario Hernandez regarding a piece of land. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Testament of Juan Pablo and Catalina Ursula], San Juan Bautista, Metepec, 1760 June 24.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 58)
    1 leaf: paper; 215 x 158 mm. Final will and testament of a man and his wife. Signed by Thomas Joseph, scribe. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Testament of Maria Teresa] San Juan Bautista, Metepec, 1780 March 25.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 59)
    1 bifolium: paper; 210 x 150 mm. Final will and testament of Maria Teresa, widow of Juan de los Santos, from Santa Cruz Tianguistenco. Signed by Simon de la Cruz, scribe. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Contract for sale of land], San Felipe Santiago, Azcapotzalco, 1739 January 8.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 6)
    3 leaves: paper; 305 x 214 mm. Bartolome Fabian and Bartolome de Vargas and Hilario Blas, of San Felipe Santiago Atzcapotzalco, sell a piece of land to D. Antonio Gonzalez Tercero, a Spaniard. Apoderado is Juan Soriano; signed by D. Hipolto Hernandez, notary. Mentions boundary dispute between the towns of Azcapotzalco and Villatlacopa. Stamp of King Philip V. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Catechism], origin unknown, [17--?].; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 60)
    1 leaf: paper; 215 x 154 mm. Fragment of a catechism, including an analysis of the Lord's Prayer. Beginning of lines alternate between "ten" and "tetl."
  - [Account book], Santa Rosalia, 1667 February-December.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 61)
    4 leaves: paper; 211 x 153 mm. Credit section of an accounting record, probably of a religious society dedicated to the rosary. Includes charitable donations, including gifts of livestock and money. Leaf count does not include cover sheet. Text in Spanish and Nahuatl.
  - [Testimony of Gregorio Sebastian], San Juan Bautista, Metepec, 1737 June 27.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 62)
    1 leaf: paper; 211 x 155 mm. Final will and testament, with instructions for mass and burial. Sebastian's wife was Monica Francisca. Includes notation by Fray Gaspar Valdivia that the mass ordered in the testament was completed. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Testament fragment], San Juan Bautista, Metepec, [1785] June 19.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 63)
    1 bifolium: paper; 210 x 153 mm. Possible addendum to a contract, and/or testament, involving Josepha Teresa (see MS 15). Paper in poor condition. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Land title for Pedro Tadeo and Maria Nolasco], Puebla de Los Angeles?, 1733 June 3.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 64)
    1 leaf: paper; 308 x 214 mm. Confirmation of ownership for a piece of land for Pedro Tadeo and his wife, Maria Nolasco. On the verso is a notation dated 1766 August 22, stating that the document was sold to Juan Hernando Casco by Blas de Santiago, a mestizo, for 4 reales. Stamp of King Philip V on recto. Text in Nahuatl and Spanish.
  - [Contract for sale of land], San Juan Bautista, Metepec, 1787 March 8.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 65)
    1 bifolium: paper; 308 x 213 mm. Purchase of land by Don Guillermo, of Santa Cruz Tianguistenco, and his wife, Petrona Severina, from Maria, in the barrio of Santiago.
  - [Contracts for sale of land, et. al], Atzcapotzalco, 1766 April 28-1804 December 6.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 66)
    4 leaves: paper; 312 x 210 mm. The first document, dated 1766, deals with a piece of land owned by Pascuala Maria, the widow of Diego Martin, and her son, Juan Partino, from San Lorenzo. The second document (bound to the first), dated 1804, is written in Spanish. In it, Doña Maria de la Merced, widow of Don Luis Bartolome Fernandez, from the barrio of Espiritu Santo, demonstrates that she purchased the land in the previous document in 1766, and now wishes to sell it to Don Juan Jose Rosano. Both documents bear the stamp of King Carolus IV.
  - [Land title for Maria Juan], San Felipe Santiago, Azcapotzalco, 1697 April 4.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 7)
    1 bifolium: paper, ill.; 310 x 212. Statement of possession for Maria Juan of San Pedro Atenco Xococalco. Property was inherited from her mother, Francisca Maria. Illustrated with an ink drawing of a house, crops, and property boundaries, showing the location of the land with reference to Azcapotzalco and Xococalco. Text in Nahuatl.
  - [Letter, Francisco de Villalobos to his ecclesiastical superior, San Martín, near Cocula], Guadalajara, 1653 March 31.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 8)
    1 leaf: paper; 310 x 214 mm. Villalobos, alcalde, charges that the people of San Martin will not cooperate to improve the church for local celebrations. Letter probably accompanied MS 9, below. Torn at upper right; staining at bottom left. Text in Spanish.
  - [Petition from the town of San Martín], Guadalajara, 1653 March 2.; 1 item. (Box 20, Folder 9)
    1 bifolium: paper; 310 x 215 mm. Criminal complaint brought by the village of San Martin, charging that the alcaldes, church officials, and Guardian of Cocula have forced them to work in town, and provide their own materials without compensation. The people express a desire to work on the unfinished church, instead. The bishop, Juan Ruiz Colmenero, ordered a formal commission of inquiry sent. Petition of the villagers is dated 1653 April 2; translation is dated 1653 March 2. Text in Nahuatl and Spanish. (Anderson, 174)